Preliminary Inventory to the Harry Schmidt Papers, 1909-1964.
Hoover Institution Archives
Harry Schmidt Papers,
1909-1964
68033
Schmidt, Harry, 1886-1968.
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 film reel 1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, orders, speeches, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relating to activities of the U.S. Marine Corps in the Pacific Theater during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
General Harry Schmidt served as Commanding General of the Fourth Marine Division during the Marshall Islands campaign and the Battle of Saipan, and as Commanding General of the Fifth Amphibious Corps during the battles of Tinian and Iwo Jima, during World War II.
During the battle for Iwo Jima, he was awarded a Gold Star in lieu of the third Distinguished Service Medal for his part in this operation. His citation reads in part, "Against determined enemy resistance and incomparable natural defenses, Major General Schmidt skillfully directed the attack of his troops to capture and occupy this strategic island. He handled the various units under his command with brilliant tactical skill. His sound judgment, distinctive administrative ability and unfailing devotion to duty were vital factors in the success of the entire operation."
Following the conclusion of hostilities, the General led the Fifth Corps in the occupation of the Japanese homeland. In 1946, he was ordered back to the United States to assume command of the Marine Training and Replacement Command, San Diego Area, California. He served in that capacity until he retired in 1948, when he was advanced to the four-star rank of General.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, orders, speeches, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs, relatig to activities of the United States Marine Corps in the Pacific Theater during World War II.
Access Points
United States. Marine Corps--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; United States--Armed Forces.
Container List
- Biographical data (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1944-1945. Includes article regarding World War II military operations (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1948-1968 concerning books, articles, and studies of Marine Corps operations in the Pacific during World War II (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence regarding christening the Iwo Jima, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Duty orders, 1909-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Commendations, 1929-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Speeches (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memoranda, 1929-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Department of the Army and Air Force pamphlets, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Five publications regarding Pacific operations, World War II (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Department of the Navy. Four statements of interest to naval commands, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Historical material regarding the Marine Corps (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Congressional Record statement, 1951 October 20, about General Schmidt (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Pamphlet, Marine Corps Memorial Foundation, ca. 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Naval Historical Foundation, list of trustees, 1956 March (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Report on air power, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographs (Box 3-4)
  Includes photographs of General H. Schmidt, various military personnel, and battles in the Pacific Theatre in World War II
  - Command turnover, October 1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Early Army career (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Family photographs, early 1900s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Flag raising ceremonies, Iwo Jima and Tinian (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Iwo Jima (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Maui (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Military ceremonies (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Military parades (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous groups (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Nagasaki and Sasebo (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Portraits (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pueget Sound Naval Shipyard, USS Iwo Jima dedication, September 1960 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Saipan (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Schmidt at official events (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Shanghai, Sasebo, and occupation of Japan (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Unidentified island (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Album of photographs (Box 4)
- Personal scrapbooks kept by General Schmidt, (two volumes), 1944-1958 (Box 4)
- "To the Shores of Iwo Jima," U.S. Navy training film (Box Film shelf)